Finding Aid to Framed Items from the Collections of The Bancroft Library
The Bancroft Library
- Collections of Framed Items
  - Framed artwork miscellany, BANC PIC 19xx.500--FR
    - Avalon and Bay, Santa Catalina Island, California [plate], [19--?]; Unknown; BANC PIC 19xx.500:031--CASE; 1 plate: transfer printing, airbrush, handcolor, and white paint; 20 x 20 cm round. Printed title (LC).
      View overlooking bay and harbor; numerous buildings clustered along shore; boats, including a ferry, visible in harbor.
    - Bird's Eye View of San Francisco from Twin Peaks, c. 1906; Unknown (Payne?); BANC PIC 19xx.500:032--FR; 1 photolithograph on paper; visible image 43.5 x 77.2 cm. Printed title (LC). Printed (below title): Burned district described by white line/ supplement to the Los Angeles Examiner, May 27, 1906; (LR): copyright, 1906, by Geo. R. Lawrence Co., Chicago.
      Broad view of San Francisco with burned district outlined.
      Bird's-eye views; Landscapes (Representations) -- California -- San Francisco; Photolithographs
    - California Pioneers of 1849, Howe, Charles E. R.; BANC PIC 19xx.500:033--FR; 1 photograph and letter press mounted on canvas: highlighted with charcoal and white chalk; visible image 146.5 x 100 cm. Printed title (LC). Printed in image (C): [...] All photographs / on this plate are those of / California Pioneers / [...] / and their children / [signed] Chas. E. R. Howe / [...] Oct. 24, 1849 / Compilator.
      Portrait heads of 556 persons, including members of Charles E.R. Howe's family. Legend with names of sitters along bottom edge.
    - The Associated Pioneers of the Territorial Days of California, [1879?]; Unknown; BANC PIC 19xx.500:034--FR; 1 photograph: albumen; image 21.2 x 56.5 cm on mount. Title on plaque (in image). Numbered legend to members in portrait (lower margin).
      Large composite group portrait of the associated pioneers including an image of General John A. Sutter in center and a large California bear flag on wall. The Association was established on Feb. 11, 1875; Sutter served as President in 1879.
    - [Landscape], Unknown (Payne?); BANC PIC 19xx.500:036--FR; 1 painting on academy board: oil; 23.4 x 30.5 cm. Partial manufacturer's label on verso of board.
      View of lake or stream with trees along shore and mountains in distance.
    - [Joseph Bryant Crockett, Jr.], Unknown; BANC PIC 19xx.500:038--FR; 1 painting: oil; visible image 75.5 x 62.8 cm. Painted signature (LL): [illegible] Handwritten (verso of frame): Crockett, Joseph Bryant, Jr.
    - [John LeConte], [18--?]; Unknown; BANC PIC 19xx.500:039--FR; 1 painting: oil; 76 x 63.5 cm.
      Bust portrait of Le Conte (1818-1891) wearing academic robe.
    - [George Bancroft], [October 5; 1880]; Richter, Gustav; BANC PIC 19xx.500:040--FR; 1 photograph (of painting): silver gelatin; visible image 47.5 x 32.9 cm, accompanying note 21.7 x 10.3 cm. Painted signature (reproduced in image LR): Gustav Richter. Blind stamp (image LR): Photogh Patsche / Berlin / Gesellschaft. Accompanying note (LC on mat): Dear Senator / except this shadow of an / old man in testimony of / sincere respect and regard / Geo. Bancroft / Oct. 5. 80. / 27 April 1881-. Copy of letter from Mr. Ralph M. Dyar to Mrs. Eleanor Bancroft regarding donation of picture (of George Bancroft).
      Three-quarter length seated portrait of bearded man holding a book.
      (unable to verify in donor files)(?)
    - [Lucy Howe Bancroft], [1872?]; Haus, L.; BANC PIC 19xx.500:041--FR; 1 painting: oil; visible oval image 74 x 61.2 cm. Painted signature (LL): L. Haus. Title (plaque on frame, LC): Lucy Howe Bancroft. Inventory stamp (verso): Oct. 1951 (#794).
      Half length portrait of an elderly woman wearing a white lace bonnet and a black lace shawl and collar, seated in a decorative chair. A brooch at her neck bears the years 1822-1872. Lucy Damaris (Howe) Bancroft (1799-1882) was the mother of Hubert Howe Bancroft and wife of Azariah Ashley Bancroft, whose portrait is the companion piece to this one. The portraits were possibly made in commemoration of the celebration of their fiftieth wedding anniversary in 1872 (see xCS71.B2).
      Oil paintings; Portraits; Bancroft, Lucy, -- 1882- -- Portraits
    - [Azariah Ashley Bancroft], [1872?]; Haus, L.; BANC PIC 19xx.500:042--FR; 1 painting: oil; visible oval image 73.3 x 61 cm. Painted signature (LR): L. Haus. Handwritten (verso stretcher): [P.C. Davis / Oakland / Paid]. Title from plaque on frame (LC). Inventory stamp (verso): Oct. 1951 (#793).
      Half-length portrait of man with a cane seated in a decorative chair. Azariah Ashley Bancroft was father of Hubert Howe Bancroft and husband of Lucy Damaris (Howe) Bancroft (1799-1882), whose portrait is the companion piece to this one. The portraits were possibly made in commemoration of the celebration of their fiftieth wedding anniversary in 1872 (see xCS71.B2).
      Oil paintings; Portraits; Bancroft, Azariah Ashley, -- 1799- -- Portraits
    - [Washington Bartlett], [ca. 1887]; Unknown; BANC PIC 19xx.500:043--FR; 1 painting: oil; 76.2 x 63.5 cm.
    - Sheridan Downey, Unknown (Payne?); BANC PIC 19xx.500:044--FR; 1 sculptural relief: copper, ink, and silver paint; visible image 39.5 x 28.8 cm. Relief signature and date (LL): H. L. Moore / - 1940 - / W. W. V. Relief title (LC). Relief (LR): Compliments of / Veterans N. M. H. Calif. / and C. L. Davison.
      Half length seated portrait of Downey writing at desk.
    - Ist California Regiment Flag, [186-?]; Unknown; BANC PIC 19xx.500:045--FR; 1 item: embroidered flag with gold braid.; 50.1 x 56 cm. Hand written note (verso): R E 1st Cal Regt. flag / George Stammerjohan / State dept. of Parks and Rep. / Sacto / an expert on this sort of thing per / Harry Morrison / 10-10-91 / ASB / also TBL book chain of command.
  - Items from: The John Bevens Bohnett, Ruth Evans Bohnett, Joan Evans Bohnett, and Barbara L. Bohnett collection of family photographs, ca. 1850-ca. 1960?; BANC PIC 2000.027
    - Portraits of Tamer Ione Barker Bohnett & Joseph Bohnett, [18--?]; Unknown; BANC PIC 2000.027:12--FR; 1 photograph with charcoal retouching; visible image 34.8 x 44.7 cm. Label (verso): Tamer Ione / Barker Bohnett / & Joseph Bohnett / 1855-1920 / 1848-1935 / John Bevens Bohnett's / Grandparents.
      Half length portrait of seated man with woman standing behind him.
      Portraits; Bohnett family -- Pictorial works
    - Portrait of Tamer Ione Barker Bohnett, [18--?]; Unknown; BANC PIC 2000.027:13--FR; 1 photograph with charcoal and white chalk retouching; visible image 39.8 x 49.6 cm. Label (verso): Tamer Ione Barker Bohnett / L.D. Bohnett's / mother / John B. Bohnett's / Grandmother.
      Bust length of young girl wearing earrings.
  - Selections: Portraits of individuals connected with the University of California, UARC PIC 13
    - [Hallidie, Andrew Smith], 1901; Beecher, Harriet Foster; UARC PIC 1300A:01; 1 painting: oil; visible image 75.5 x 65.5 cm. Incised signature and date (LR): Harriet Foster Beecher 1901. Handwritten (verso of frame): IS [15?] in notation. Label (UL verso): Loaned to Office of the Chancellor 30 October 1980; (Label tied to frame): 271 (inventory of 1951).
      Half length seated portrait.
    - [Tompkins, Edward], 1872; Cogswell, W; UARC PIC 1300A:02; 1 painting: oil; visible dome top image 115.5 x 90 cm. Painted signature and date (LR): W. Cogswell / 1872. Handwritten (canvas verso): Edwd Tompkins / 1872. Manufacturer's stamp (canvas verso) from Snow & Roos Picture frames. Stamp (canvas verso, stretcher, and frame) Inventory October 1951 (#265). Handwritten (UL verso of frame): 9 in rotation / 2 on face / 6 inches from [rail?].
      Three-quarter length seated portrait of Tompkins (1815-1872) in upholstered chair holding Register of the University of California, [Oakland?]. Landscape vista beyond column to left. A gift from Tompkins established the Agassiy Professorship of Oriental Languages and Literature in 1872.
      Transferred from Hearst storage in 1973/.[sic]
      Oil paintings; Portraits; University of California, Berkeley -- Portraits
    - [Haight, Henry Huntley], 1878; Cogswell, W; UARC PIC 1300A:03; 1 painting: oil; visible dome top image 125.1 x 99.8 cm. Painted signature and date (LR): W. Cogswell / 1878. Plaque (LC on frame): Henry Huntley Haight / 1825-1878 / Governor of California / 1868-1871 / 7. Stamp (canvas verso and stretcher) Inventory October 1951 (#263). Handwritten stretcher (UC): 16 in rotation / 6 on face; (frame verso): 10; 9.
      Three-quarter length standing portrait of Haight (1825-1878) with one arm behind back and the other resting on a draped plinth.
      Transferred from Hearst storage in 1973.
    - [LeConte, Joseph], [ca. 1860-1865]; Unknown; UARC PIC 1300A:04; 1 painting: oil; visible image 70.2 cm x 54.8 cm. Handwritten (verso of stretcher): #684.
      Bust length portrait of Le Conte (1823-1901), professor of geology and noted evolutionist.
      Transferred from the Geology Department (via Margaret Gennaro), 7 December 1984.
      Oil paintings; Portraits; University of California, Berkeley -- Portraits; LeConte, Joseph, -- 1823-1901 -- Portraits
    - [LeConte, Joseph], 1886; Keith, William; UARC PIC 1300A:05
      Restored in late 1970s(?) with funds donated by the LeConte family. Restoration reported in Bancroftiana 78:10, with an illustration.
      1954 inventory #274.
    - [LeConte, John], 1877; Lussier; UARC PIC 1300A:06; 1 painting: oil; visible image 121.3 x 91 cm. Painted signature and date (LC): Lussier's Pt. 1877. Label (verso): 704.
      Three-quarter length portrait of LeConte wearing an academic robe seated in a carved Gothic style wooden chair.
    - [Hager, John S.], 1892; Neal, Davis; UARC PIC 1300A:07; 1 painting: oil; visible image 72.5 x 54.4 cm. Painted signature and date (UL): David Neal 1892. Plaque (LC on frame): Painted by / David Neal. Label (LR on image):10. Handwritten (frame verso): #6; 16. Label (verso): 272 (inventory of 1951).
    - [Paget, Felicien Victor], [1895?]; Richardson, Mary Curtis; UARC PIC 1300A:08; 1 painting: oil; visible image 106.5 x 77.5 cm. Painted signature (LL): Mary Curtis Richardson. Painted signature (LR): Mary Curtis Richardson. Inventory stamp (verso): Oct. 1951 (# 275).
      Three-quarter length seated portrait of Professor Felicien Victor Paget (1833-1903) holding a book.
      Oil paintings; Portraits; Paget, Felicien Victor, -- 1833-1903. -- Portraits
    - [Slate, Frederick], [18--]; Richardson, Mary Curtis; UARC PIC 1300A:09; 1 painting on canvas mounted on board; oil: visible image 52.1 x 44.3 cm. Biographical information on verso.
      Bust portrait of Slate (1852-1930), U.C. Professor of Physics from 1875-1918 and one of the first graduating students at the Berkeley campus in 1873.
    - [Felton, John Brooks], [18--]; Shaw, Stephen William; UARC PIC 1300A:10; 1 painting: oil; 76.5 x 63.8 cm. Painted cypher (LL): [SWS]. Label (LL on print): 17.
      Half length portrait of Felton (1827-1877).
    - [Waymire, James Andrew], [188-?]; Unknown; UARC PIC 1300A:11; 1 painting on canvas: oil; oval image 73.3 x 60.7 cm. Handwritten (verso): Judge Waymire. Inventory stamp (verso): Oct. 1951 (#277).
      Half length portrait of Judge Waymire (b. 1842) who was appointed to Superior Court of San Francisco, 1881.
    - [Swift, John F. ], [18--]; Unknown; UARC PIC 1300A:12; 1 painting: oil; visible image 75.3 x 60.7 cm. Handwritten label (verso): John / F. / Swift.
      Bust length of John Franklin Swift (1829-1891).
    - [Haviland, John T.], Unknown; UARC PIC 1300A:13; 1 painting: oil; visible oval image 59.5 x 46.5 cm. Inventory stamp (verso): Oct. 1951 (#17). Handwritten (LL, verso and on label attached to wire): 17.
      Bust length portrait of bearded man.
    - [Stebbins, Horatio], 1895; Vermorcken, Frederick M.; UARC PIC 1300A:14; 1 painting: oil; visible image 120.5 x 90.5 cm. Printed signature and date (UR): F. M Vermorcken / 1895/. Label (LR on image): 14; (UR on frame): Horatio / Stebbens. Handwritten (UR on frame): 262 (in chalk). Inventory October 1951 (canvas verso stretcher and label taped to frame) (#262). Printed labels (stretcher): 2; 14. Handwritten (verso of frame): 6.
      Three-quarter length seated portrait of Stebbens (1821-1902) wearing ruby ring, with arm on cloth covered table; papers, pen, and inkwell on table. Stebbins was appointed Regent of the University of California in 1868 and 1878.
    - [Phelps, Timothy Guy], [18--]; Withrow, Evelyn Almond; Williams, Elizabeth; UARC PIC 1300A:15; 1 painting: oil; visible image 74.5 x 62 cm. Painted signature (LL): E. Almond Withrow / San Francisco. Title (label on verso). Label (LR on painting): 22.
      Bust portrait of Phelps (1824-1899).
      1951 inventory has Williams; document listing materials to be transferred from UAM (Univeristy Art Museum) has Williams lined out and Withrow written in.
    - [Miller, Albert], [1887?]; Yates, Frederick; UARC PIC 1300A:16; 1 painting: oil; visible image 91 x 72 cm. Painted signature and date (LR): Fred Yates [1887?]. Handwritten (verso of frame): 15658-13. Stamp (verso of frame): Oct. 1951 Inventory (#409).
      Profile three-quarter length portrait of Miller (1828-1900) reading a paper, seated in a leather-covered wooded chair. Miller was appointed as Regent of the University of California in 1887 and again from 1890-1900.
    - [Toland, Hugh H.], [186-?]; Unknown; UARC PIC 1300A:17; 1 print on paper mounted on canvas: lithograph; oval image 69.5 x 52.3 cm. Handwritten (verso of canvas): Dr. Hugh H. Toland / Donor of the Toland Medical School / to the University. Handwritten [inventory] #342 on canvas verso and label taped to stretcher.
      Bust portrait of Toland (1806-1880), founder of the Toland Medical College in 1862 which became the University of California School of Medicine, San Francisco.
    - [Sproul, Robert Gordon], [ca. 1934]; Thomas, S. Seymour; UARC PIC 1300A:25; 1 painting: oil; visible image 115.5 cm x 88 cm. Painted signature (LL).
      Sproul was president of the University of California from 1930 to 1958.
    - [Kellogg, Martin], 1901; Peck, Orrin; UARC PIC 1300A:24; 1 painting: oil; visible image 105 cm x 96 cm. Painted signature and date (LL).
      Kellogg was president of the University of California from 1893 to 1899.
    - [Dwinelle, John Whipple], 1873; Cogswell, W; UARC PIC 1300A:23; 1 painting: oil; visible image 115 cm x 90 cm. Painted signature and date (LL).
      Standing portrait of a man holding Assembly Bill #583, "to create and organize the University of California."
    - [Campbell, William Wallace], 1931; Thomas, S. Seymour; UARC PIC 1300A:22; 1 painting: oil; visible image 114.5 cm x 87 cm. Handwritten (verso) on stretcher frame: Dr. William Wallace Campbell, 1862, painted at La Crescenta, January 1931.
      Campbell was president of the University of California from 1929 to 1930.
    - [Durant, Henry], UARC PIC 1300A:21; 1 painting: oil; visible image 109 cm x 81.5 cm. Painted signature (LR, hidden by frame): B I[rwin?].
      Durant was president of the University of California from 1870 to 1872.
    - [Gilman, Daniel Coit], Unknown; UARC PIC 1300A:20; 1 painting: oil; visible image 110.5 cm x 75.5 cm.
      Gilman was president of the University of California from 1872 to 1875.
    - [LeConte, John], Unknown; UARC PIC 1300A:19; 1 painting: oil; visible image 100.5 cm x 70 cm.
      Le Conte was president of the University of California from 1876 to 1881.
    - [Reid, William Thomas], Richardson, Mary Curtis; UARC PIC 1300A:18; 1 painting: oil; visible image 101.5 cm x 72.5 cm. Painted signature (LL).
      Reid was president of the University of California from 1881 to 1885.
    - [Barrows, David P. (David Prescott)], Unknown; UARC PIC 1300A:26; 1 painting: oil; visible image 113.5 cm x 88 cm.
      Barrows was president of the University of California from 1919 to 1923.
    - [Davis, Horace], 1914; Richardson, Mary Curtis; UARC PIC 1300A:27; 1 painting: oil; visible image 105 cm x 79 cm. Painted signature and date (LL).
      Davis was the sixth president of the University of California.
  - Items from: University of California, Berkeley campus views, UARC PIC 03
    - View from the university grounds at Berkeley 1874: Mt. Tamalpais (in distance), Watkins, Carleton E.; UARC PIC 03:020--FR; 1 photograph: albumen; visible image 40.7 x 52.4 cm. Handwritten title and date (LC): View from University grounds at Berkeley-1874. / Mt. Tamalpais (in the distance); (LR): C. E. Watkins.
      Mammoth plate view of South and North Halls of the University of California, and a few homes and orchards of the town of Berkeley. View taken from the hillside (near present Memorial Stadium) southeast of the builidings, looking northwest.
      University of California, Berkeley -- Pictorial works; Universities and colleges -- California -- Berkeley -- Photographs
    - View from the university ground [sic] at Berkeley: the Golden Gate (in the distance), 1874; Watkins, Carleton E.; UARC PIC 03:226a--FR; 1 photograph: albumen; visible image 40.6 x 52 cm. Handwritten title and date (LC): View from the university ground [sic] at Berkeley / the Golden Gate (in the distance) 1874; (LR): C.E. Watkins.
      Mammoth plate view of South and North Halls of the University of California, taken from the hillside to the east, looking west toward the San Francisco Bay.